# Ravindra Marathe, CEng, MSc, PhD

Process Safety & Risk Manager, GlaxoSmithKline, Irvine, KA11 5AP, UK

Tel: +44-7538260846 (cell), +44-1294847161 (day), Email: ravindra.p.marathe@gsk.com

#### **SUMMARY**

I am an ambitious process safety engineering professional with 16-year experience in high hazard process industry plus 4 years in R&D seeking leadership opportunities in safety and risk consulting. I am IChemE Chartered and a Lean Sigma Greenbelt and have proven experience in safety management & working with people across geographies & industries.

#### **CORE COMPETENCIES**

- Safety leadership & risk management regulatory compliance, EHS management system, ALARP, COMAH, PHR
- Behavioral safety & human factors competency management, human error, life saving rules, living safety
- Lean Sigma & Change BAT benchmarking, continuous improvement, Bowties, incident investigation, deep dives
- Process safety engineering DSEAr/ AtEx, inertion, dispersion, electrostatics, asphyxiation, OBRA, air emissions etc.

#### **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

## GlaxoSmithKline, Irvine, UK

## **Process Safety & Risk Manager**

2013- present

- Delivered y-o-y reduction in safety incidents & loss events for 8 years via PSM program.
- Shared best practice on EHS and engineering standards at GSK network PS Community of Practice.
- Chaired strategic safety assessments incl. PHR, HAZID, ALARP as well as HAZOP, What If, SIL, LOPA, Functional safety.
- Conducted L1/L2 audits and barrier effectiveness verification at Irvine and key supplier offsite.
- Deployed bowtie model to risk management at Irvine and drove risk reduction projects.
- Developed and deployed PS Competency development framework incl training, workshops, e-learning, videos etc.
- Delivered high safety maturity for site in audits by internal and external auditors, regulator & insurer.
- Added value by employed Lean Sigma tools, root cause, barrier analysis, for incident investigations.
- Improved work practices and reduced risk following safety critical task analysis, human reliability assessments.

#### GlaxoSmithKline, Irvine, UK

## Senior Process Engineer

2007- 2012

- Implemented efficiency and safety improvement solutions incl. capacity expansion, pressure relief, PLC upgrade
- Developed site standard for plant commissioning and Operational qualification.
- Modified design specifications, P&IDs, HAC drawings for change control & projects.
- Standardised process engineering ways of working for software downloads and change management.

## **Eurochem Corporation, Singapore**

# Scientist – catalysis R&D

2005 - 2007

- Executed catalyst synthesis & testing program for innovative syngas hydrogenation.
- Designed and commissioned reactor system, operation and data analysis.

# Birla Institute of Technology & Science (BITS) Pilani, India Assistant Lecturer of Chemical Engineering

2001

Taught courses & laboratory sessions in Process Control and Measurement Techniques.

## Reliance Petroleum Ltd, Jamnagar Refinery India

## Process Engineer – crude oil

1998 - 1999

- Operational qualification and commissioning of crude oil & solvent storage and piping system.
- Plant troubleshooting, safety improvements, tank level system calibration, oil loss calculations.

## Hindustan Unilever and Godrej Soaps, India

## **Process Engineering Intern - FMCG manufacturing**

1996 - 1997

- Mass and Energy balance calculations for soap manufacture process.
- Manufacturing and packaging line scheduling study.

# Ravindra Marathe, CEng, MSc, PhD

Process Safety & Risk Manager,
GlaxoSmithKline, Irvine, KA11 5AP, UK

Tel: +44-7538260846 (cell), +44-1294847161 (day), Email: ravindra.p.marathe@gsk.com

#### **KEY BEHAVIOURS AND SKILLS**

## **Team building and Knowledge Transfer**

- \* Managed a team of process engineers at Eurochem, safety engineer and interns at GSK Irvine.
- \* Led Irvine process engineering to the network energy kaizen and solvent recovery partnership with other sites.
- \* Delivered capability improvement via competency framework, training programs and workshops.
- \* Worked with external consultants on powder testing, HAC, OBRA, PHAST & implemented recommendations.

## Leadership and working across boundaries

- \* Engaged with site SLT and Primary & Antibiotics EHS Governance forums for escalation and response to issues.
- \* Led major accident Deep dives, L1, L2 audits, GES gap analysis, hosted HSE inspections, audit & assurance visits.
- Employed Lean Sigma tools in change management, energy and waste minimization.
- \* Deployed best in network standards on PHIRA, Bowtie, basis of safety and human factors on site and PAM COP.

#### **EDUCATION**

## MSc in Safety and Risk Management - Distinction

Heriot Watt University, Edinburgh UK

Focus on human factors in major accident hazards

Certificate in Innovation and Entrepreneurship, University of Edinburgh, UK

# **PhD in Chemical Engineering**

National University of Singapore

Focus on adsorption based natural gas separation

#### M Eng in Chemical Engineering

Birla Institute of Technology & Science (BITS), Pilani, India

Focus on Trickle bed reactors

#### B Tech in Chemical Technology - Distinction

Laxminarayan Institute of Technology (LIT), Nagpur University, India.

#### **AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS**

2013 - 20	GSK values awards and recognition - numerous
2012	Lean Sigma Green belt, GSK.
2010	Team member in GSK President's Roll of Honour for the Irvine Energy Program.
2009	GSK Excellence Recognition Award for Energy Program and Solvent Recovery baseline.
2008	Irvine Excellence Recognition Award for OQ Standard Ways of Working at Irvine.
2001-2005	Full Doctoral Fellowship at the National University of Singapore.